<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Selected Talks | Lucas Porth</title><link>/event/</link><atom:link href="/event/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Selected Talks</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Lucas Porth 2021-2024</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 19:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>/media/icon_hub7d3a1b4174aa7987c75d6b0f4968df4_881_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Selected Talks</title><link>/event/</link></image><item><title>Ein Bissen Kosmologie - Wie bestimmen wir die Zutaten des Kosmos?</title><link>/talk/ein-bissen-kosmologie-wie-bestimmen-wir-die-zutaten-des-kosmos/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/talk/ein-bissen-kosmologie-wie-bestimmen-wir-die-zutaten-des-kosmos/</guid><description>&lt;p>Public talk aiming to explain how cosmological constraints are obtained. After motivating that different cosmological parameters influence the visual appeareance of dark matter snapshots from a simulation, we show that this visual difference can be compressed into summary statistics like the 3D correlation fuction. We then show the cosmology-dependence of the correlation function and use it to visualize the likelihood contours in the Omegam-S8 plane. We then present an interpret the cosmological constraints of the KiDS-1000 analysis and give an outlook about the prospect of future missions, such as Euclid.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Von krummen Lichstrahlen zur dunklen Seite des Universums</title><link>/talk/von-krummen-lichstrahlen-zur-dunklen-seite-des-universums/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/talk/von-krummen-lichstrahlen-zur-dunklen-seite-des-universums/</guid><description>&lt;p>Talk introducing the topic of gravitational lensing to undergraduate physics students. After a short conceptual and historical introduction we visualize the strong lensing effect of a galaxy cluster. We then move on to introduce the weak lensing effect of cosmic shear and motivate why a large number of sources is neccessary for a detailed reconstruction of the underlying mass field. We close by giving an overview of how this data can be used to get cosmological constraints with stage III surveys and outline the potential of stage IV surveys.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The video used to show the strong lensing effect of a galaxy cluster can be retrieved &lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1ZT5eG2HH2_Laq3Ac5u2azOTO3hMu9xHF/view?usp=sharing" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Efficient Estimation of Higher-Order Cosmic Shear Statistics</title><link>/talk/efficient-estimation-of-higher-order-cosmic-shear-statistics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Dec 2023 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/talk/efficient-estimation-of-higher-order-cosmic-shear-statistics/</guid><description>&lt;p>Talk based on the &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.08601" target="_blank" rel="noopener">paper&lt;/a> on efficient estimation of third-order shear correlation functions and an application to the KiDS-1000 data&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The information content of Projected Galaxy Fields</title><link>/talk/the-information-content-of-projected-galaxy-fields/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/talk/the-information-content-of-projected-galaxy-fields/</guid><description>&lt;p>Talk based on the &lt;a href="../publication/2023_infocontentprojgalfields/">first&lt;/a> paper on the information content of projected galaxy fields&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Fast Estimation of Aperture Mass Statistics</title><link>/talk/fast-estimation-of-aperture-mass-statistics/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2020 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/talk/fast-estimation-of-aperture-mass-statistics/</guid><description>&lt;p>Talk based on the &lt;a href="../publication/aperturemass2020/">first&lt;/a> paper on fast estimation of aperture mass statistics&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>